<apoena>
<cabecalhorss> <cdrss>422</cdrss><endrss>thehavananote.com/atom.xml</endrss><cdtipdoc>1</cdtipdoc><dsctip>RSS</dsctip><cdfont>361</cdfont><dscfont> THE HAVANA NOTE </dscfont><cdtipfont>2</cdtipfont><nmtipfont> INDEPENDENTE </nmtipfont> </cabecalhorss>
<item>
   <title>
U.S. Chamber Renews Call for Action on Cuba
</title>
   <link>
SEM LINK
</link>
    tag:thehavananote.com,2010://1.495 
   
    2010-08-25T15:46:48Z 
    2010-08-25T16:46:47Z 
   
   <description>
 Photo: US Chamber of Commerce/Ian Wagreich While Congress is on recess this month, the U.S. Chamber of Commerce is working to get Cuba legislation on its agenda when members return in September. Last week, following a New York Times...
</description>
    
       Anya Landau French 
       http://thehavananote.com/anyalandaufrench.html 
    
   
   
    
         
Photo:  US Chamber of Commerce/Ian Wagreich 
While Congress is on recess this month, the U.S. Chamber of Commerce is working to get Cuba legislation on its agenda when members return in September.  Last week, following a  New York Times  report on changes the Obama administration is expected to make to U.S. Cuba travel rules, the Chamber's Maria Medrano  teed up  the Chamber's expectations for such a move:
 "President Obama s moves to broaden the scope of travel--as much can be done by executive action—should send a clear signal to Congress that the administration is open to, and has done all it can, to expand engagement with Cuba.  These actions by the administration and legislation currently in Congress indicate we are on the brink of changing our strategy toward Cuba.  After 50 years of a failing policy it shouldn t be so hard to make this final leap and lift the travel ban for the good of the Cuban people." 
But just to make sure Congress got the message, the Chamber's top lobbyist, Bruce Josten, sent a  letter  yesterday to the Foreign Affairs Committee, in whose court the bill now sits.
 "The U.S. Chamber of Commerce, the world s largest business federation representing the interests of more than three million businesses and organizations of every size, sector, and region, urges you to schedule a mark-up of H.R. 4645, the Travel Restriction Reform and Export Enhancement Act.
It is time to end the unproductive preoccupation with an aging and moribund communist regime, and begin to lay the groundwork for a U.S. role in the future of Cuba.  Recent moves in both Havana and Washington indicate that the time is right to adjust U.S. policy toward Cuba in favor of a strategy that will encourage positive change on the island.
Because of the need to reform U.S. policy toward Cuba, the Chamber urges the Committee to report this legislation to the full House swiftly and without amendment so that the House can consider and approve this measure in the very near term."  
        What's most interesting about what's in the letter (and let's be honest that the most important part of a letter from the US Chamber is the letterhead) is what's not.  The letter makes only the most fleeting reference to potential gains to U.S. businesses of the legislation it's pushing, and focuses instead on the political question of how to reform Cuba, and how to make life better for the Cuban people.
 "Getting U.S.-Cuba policy right matters, because the U.S. response will send a signal to the wider world about American values, including helping neighbors who have suffered
oppression and poverty under a callous dictator. U.S. policy should consider strategies that are
more likely to advance democracy, the rule of law, and a brighter future for the people of Cuba
and bring commercial benefits to the United States, rather than focus on how increased tourism
and sales to the island will impact the Cuban regime." 
Perhaps this is a pre-buttle to critics who regularly claim that farm and business groups only don't care about the people and just want to stuff Fidel Castro's pockets with cash.  While I understand the urge to defend against such charges, it won't stop them from coming.  The truth is, the most virulent opposition to a change in tack with Cuba cannot afford a rational meet-half-way sort of conversation, and will always attack reformers no matter what reasons they offer for proposed reform.  So, go ahead Chamber of Commerce, heed your motto proudly (as you so often do): "fighting for your business." 
    
</item>
<item>
   <title>
More Prisoners Released as Cuban Catholic Church Responds to Critics
</title>
   <link>
SEM LINK
</link>
    tag:thehavananote.com,2010://1.494 
   
    2010-08-24T16:21:56Z 
    2010-08-24T19:53:36Z 
   
   <description>
 Image available: http://archive.catholicherald.co.uk/images/articles/a0000429.jpg The Cuban Catholic Archdiocese announced today the expected release of six more Cuban political prisoners, bringing the total number of prisoners released by the Raul Castro government since July to 32. Secretary Clinton has expressed the...
</description>
    
       Anya Landau French 
       http://thehavananote.com/anyalandaufrench.html 
    
   
   
    
         
I mage available: http://archive.catholicherald.co.uk/images/articles/a0000429.jpg 
The Cuban Catholic Archdiocese ##a  http://palabranueva.net/contens/pn_notic.htm#1042" /a## today the expected release of six more Cuban political prisoners, bringing the total number of prisoners released by the Raul Castro government since July to 32.
Secretary Clinton has expressed the United States government's willingness to receive some of the recently arrived political prisoners from Spain.  But as reporters encountered at yesterday's  Daily Press Briefing  at the State Department, it's complicated.  It's one thing to grant an asylum request to someone who would otherwise be persecuted if you don't grant asylum, it's quite another to grant such a request to someone who no longer actually needs it.   
Further complicating the situation is that the wet-foot dry-foot immigration policy - a sort of Green Card fast-track for Cubans who manage to slip into the U.S. illegally (which is significantly easier from just 90 miles away) - might not apply to these ex-political prisoners.  Why?  Because the only reasonable way to make it in to the U.S. from Spain is to fly in on an airplane, which authorities won't permit you to do without a visa (and there's usually a long line for those).  So, the newly-released Cubans may have to make do in Spain for some time yet.
Meanwhile, the editors of the Catholic Church's lay newspaper have issued a forceful  response  to a group of more than 100 Cuban dissidents, who sent  a letter  to Pope Benedict to protest the Cuban Catholic church's "regrettable and embarassing" intervention with the Cuban government on behalf of Cuban political prisoners.  The signers fault the Church for accepting "forced exile" for the prisoners, which, with families in tow to Spain, they write, amounts to an "exodus".   
        While it's not surprising to hear criticism of the Cuban government for what appears to be its attempt to export its opposition, it's less clear why the Catholic Church is held to blame for what is essentially the prisoner's own decision about whether to accept the terms of the Cuban government's offer.  Afterall, half a dozen prisoners - whom the Cuban government appears to be saving til the end of this episode - have already announced they won't go if made the offer.  So, eventually, we'll see whether the prisoners were forced to leave the country or, rather that they chose the bird-in-hand - freedom in exile - when it was so offered.  And is it so surprising that these Cubans who withstood horrendous prison conditions, and would certainly not have it easy in Cuba upon their release, might choose this least bad option?  If it is not wrong for them to choose their freedom wherever they may enjoy it, why is it wrong for the Church to help them achieve that freedom?
The row always comes down to this - whether or not the Church does or should play a role in the political destiny of Cuba, and in this case mediate between the Cuban government and Cubans who consider themselves the "opposition", or whether the Church's role is more aptly to minister to Cubans in need.  The Church response makes clear the role it has chosen (my translation below):
 "The efforts undertaken by the Catholic Church in Cuba does not represent any support or act of legitimizing of any temporary power, neither governmental nor of opposition. The efforts have instead been an evangelical task, to the extent possible, to help lessen the pain and suffering of a group of Cubans that were in prison, as well as of their relatives.
On the other hand, if our Episcopate were to seek to prove its credentials, it would be to have maintained, throughout many years, its independence and autonomy with respect to powers inside and outside Cuba. Of that, many Cuban Catholics feel very proud."  
    
</item>
<item>
   <title>
Hope Springs Eternal in US-Cuban Relations
</title>
   <link>
SEM LINK
</link>
    tag:thehavananote.com,2010://1.493 
   
    2010-08-23T13:38:58Z 
    2010-08-23T16:20:21Z 
   
   <description>
 Photo credit: Darkwind They say timing is everything. But in U.S.-Cuban relations, timing is often nothing more than a missed opportunity. Everyone has their own theory about these things. Back in 1996, analysts thought it was a most opportune...
</description>
    
       Anya Landau French 
       http://thehavananote.com/anyalandaufrench.html 
    
   
   
    
         
 Photo credit:  Darkwind   
They say timing is everything.  But in U.S.-Cuban relations, timing is often nothing more than a missed opportunity.  Everyone has their own theory about these things.  Back in 1996, analysts thought it was a most opportune moment for improved relations.  The Helms-Burton Act was stalled and President Clinton appeared to have no intention of signing it.  And then Cuban migs shot down two civilian aircraft that Cuba claimed had violated its airspace.  (The group that sent the planes on their mission that day, Brothers to the Rescue, claim they did not violate Cuban airspace that day - though indeed they had previously, even overflying and leafletting Havana.)  It might have been an opportune moment, but it turned out not to be. 
And then there were the early 2000's, when a Republican-controlled Congress repeatedly bucked its President, voting to end enforcement of the decades old travel ban on Cuba.  The Senate Foreign Relations Committee even voted out a bill to lift the ban outright.  U.S.-Cuban agriculture ties were at their tightest, and U.S. Cuba food export fever was at its highest.  But President Bush had committed to embargo supporters, and his veto threats ensured that House and Senate leaders yanked Cuba reforms out of every bill they rode along.  And then in 2003, with Congress leading the charge for U.S. policy reform, Cuban authorities rounded up 75 dissident activists and sending them to jail for collaborating with the U.S. enemy.  It could have been a transformational moment, but it turned out not to be.
And then of course, in 2006 and 2008, Democrats swept through Congress, and won the presidency.  The new president was even on record as opposed to the U.S. embargo of Cuba, and campaigned on a foreign policy that would win back the respect of the world.  Though Cuba policy seemed such obvious low-hanging fruit, the new administration and Congress failed to grasp the opportunity, particularly in the midst of crushing domestic and international crises and larger priorities like healthcare legislation.  Meanwhile, Fidel Castro fell gravely ill in 2006, retired from sight and from the presidency in Cuba, and his more pragmatic brother officially took the reins in 2008, broaching topics and raising criticisms of the Cuban system never discussed under the elder Castro's watch.  It should have been the long awaited breakthrough moment, but it turned out not to be.
And here we are in 2010.   
        Last year, the Obama administration broadly authorized family visits and remittances to Cuba (to its credit) but otherwise just tinkered timidly around the edges, despite broad authority to do much, much more.   Raul Castro has spotlighted a heap of problems in Cuba and implemented just a few solutions, ever so slowly ("We have no right to make mistakes" he said recently).  
While both governments largely eschewed hyperbolic, confrontational rhetoric, and restarted migration talks suspended by the Bush administration, underlying causes of bilateral tensions continued to fester, including Cuban government supporters' harassment of dissidents (which, whether the Cuban government thinks it's our business or not, the U.S. considers to be its business on principle), and the U.S. government's careless continuation of USAID democracy-building programs expanded under the Bush administration.  By the close of Barack Obama's first year and Raul Castro's second year in their respective offices, bilateral relations were headed south, with an American citizen in a Cuban jail, apparently after traveling to Cuba as a tourist, but working on a U.S. government contract.
Given these tales I've just retold, it surprises me that I actually think that the stars could yet align in these dog days of summer 2010.  And if they do, we might all have the Cuban Catholic Church to thank for its role in triggering a series of events this summer that offer renewed hope of progress in Cuba and the United States.  Consider that Raul Castro's government - as part of an ongoing dialogue with Church leaders - has released 25 dissidents jailed under Fidel Castro in 2003.  (The Church, which has helped broker space for the Ladies in White's marches in Havana, also seems to have played a role in ending the intimidation of the mother of the Cuban prisoner who died after a hunger strike back in February, who  led  a march in her son's honor yesterday).  And note that this summer Fidel Castro began a series of seemingly random public appearances just as the releases began, but said not one word about the dissidents or about the domestic economic restructuring being discussed under his brother's direction.  
At the same time, the U.S. Congress has been flexing its muscles vis a vis Cuba travel restrictions, and even passed a bill out of a key House committee this summer, and the Obama administration is now even said to be getting into the game.  (Cuba's Catholic Cardinal Jaime Ortega, who has met personally with Raul Castro, even traveled to Washington this summer and met with President Obama's National Security Advisor.)  Depending on how ambitious the Obama Administration's expected  rule changes  turn out to be, they could in turn motivate Congress to finish the job and lift travel restrictions for all Americans when it returns from summer campaigning next month. 
And now, New Mexico Governor Bill Richardson is  back in Cuba  for the week on a follow up to his trade mission to the island last year.  Now, I'm sure New Mexico must have something to sell to Cuba, but but it's hard not to speculate that this trip could somehow result in the release of Alan Gross, the American in Cuban jail since December 2009.  Afterall, Bill Richardson is known for forays into the most inhospitable environments to negotiate prisoner releases.  (Of course, if Richardson manages this trip the way he did the  last one , arguably playing more to Little Havana than to Havana, the chances dim considerably.)  But if the Cuban government manages to do what the two governments have failed at for many years - to seize the right moment - and it releases Mr. Gross in the next few weeks, that would certainly offer tremendous momentum to Congress, which has just enough time left before the fall elections to take a vote on a bill that would lift the travel ban and boost U.S. farm exports to the island.  
A lot can, and often does, go wrong, when it comes to the United States and Cuba.  And yet, here in Washington, hope, however improbable, springs eternal. 
    
</item>
<item>
   <title>
Don t Miss These
</title>
   <link>
SEM LINK
</link>
    tag:thehavananote.com,2010://1.492 
   
    2010-08-19T13:31:12Z 
    2010-08-19T14:51:40Z 
   
   <description>
 While we do not normally do news round ups here on The Havana Note, seeing as our friend over at the Cuban Triangle who usually covers all the odds and ends is on vacation, we thought we would take...
</description>
    
       Nicholas Maliska 
       nmaliska 
    
   
   
    
         
While we do not normally do news round ups here on The Havana Note, seeing as our friend over at the  Cuban Triangle  who usually covers all the odds and ends is on vacation, we thought we would take a look at some of the news stories that have flown under the radar in the shadow of the coming administrative changes.  
Café Fuerte  reports  on the trial of three Cuban-American exiles that staged an armed incursion into Cuba in 2001.  The three men were caught with a range of weapons and reportedly confessed that they had planned to commit violent actions against the island, which the Cuban government has called an act of terrorism.  After waiting eight years for a trial, the three men, who had been associated with the militant anti-Castro exile group Alpha 66, received sentences of 30 years to life in prison.  The timing of this is quite interesting, as the State Department recently released its  terrorism report  on August 5th, which once again designates Cuba as a State Sponsor of Terrorism.  The report, however, does not mention any of the terrorist actions committed against Cuba that originated in the U.S.
Five dissidents were arrested on Monday August 16, 2010, after peacefully protesting on the steps in front of the University of Havana and chanting Down with the Castros.  Two of the five were released on Wednesday, but the rest remain in police custody, according to the  Miami Herald .  This seems to be another instance of the Cuban government holding opposition activists for short periods of detainment rather than sentencing them to longer prison terms.  Elizardo Sanchez of the Cuban Commission for Human Rights and National Reconciliation, is  paraphrased in the Miami Herald article, explaining that "Police technically have 10 days to file charges, but can obtain extensions of the deadline".
Reina Luisa Tamayo, the mother of the prisoner who died earlier this year after a hunger strike, has been facing sustained harassment from "pro-government mobs," which have prevented her from going to church and marching through the streets with relatives to mourn her dead son, according to this  AP article .   
        The American Ballet Theater Company has been  approved  by OFAC to perform in Cuba for the first time in over fifty years.  This seems to be progress from earlier this year when OFAC ##a  http://thehavananote.com/2010/02/groundhog_day_in_the_usa_1.html#more" /a a  http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-11010321" /a## notes:
 The BBC's Michael Voss, in Havana, said the tour almost had to be called off for financial reasons after Washington refused to allow the company's sponsors to support the tour.
Cuban authorities stepped in and agreed to cover the dancers' accommodation and other expenses during the festival, he added. 
Depending on the scope of the Obama Administration s soon to be announced changes on non-tourist travel, unnecessary hindrances that have prevented more mutually beneficial cultural exchanges to take place may be removed.  
 
    
</item>
<item>
   <title>
Cuba Travel on the Horizon?
</title>
   <link>
SEM LINK
</link>
    tag:thehavananote.com,2010://1.491 
   
    2010-08-18T19:55:25Z 
    2010-08-18T20:07:21Z 
   
   <description>
 Rumors that the Obama Administration is preparing to announce measures that will ease travel restrictions to Cuba have been circulating for several weeks, but the news now seems to be official with multiple knowledgeable sources indicating that the announcement...
</description>
    
       Nicholas Maliska 
       nmaliska 
    
   
   
    
         
Rumors that the Obama Administration is preparing to announce measures that will ease travel restrictions to Cuba have been circulating for several weeks, but the news now seems to be official with multiple knowledgeable  sources  indicating that the  announcement  will come within the next week or two.
The  scope  of the changes is still unknown and could range from a limited loosening of restrictions on specific licenses back to where it was during the Clinton years to permitting general licenses in all twelve categories of travel, which would facilitate the greatest amount of non-tourist visits to Cuba. The changes will certainly be the biggest development in U.S. policy towards Cuba since President Obama announced the  easing of restrictions  on Cuban American travel and remittances to the island in April 2009 and will send a long overdue signal that the Obama Administration takes Cuba policy seriously.
In the context of U.S.-Cuban relations more broadly, some analysts have been framing this development in the context of a tit-for-tat diplomatic maneuvering with the Cuban government. Earlier this summer after negotiations with the Catholic Church in Cuba, Raul Castro announced that 52 political prisoners would be  released  (26 of which have been freed and sent to Spain thus far). The easing of travel restrictions, they say, is Washington's response to the release of the political prisoners.  
        However, these changes have likely been in the works for some time as Julia Sweig, director of the Latin America program at the Council on Foreign Relations  indicated  in a recent Washington Post article: "It's a little easier to do it, given the political prisoners' release. But I think they were going to do it anyway."
Those looking at the Obama Administration's announcement as a move in a tit-for-tat framework will expect another gesture from the Cuban government in turn (such as the release of Alan Gross, the USAID contractor  imprisoned  since last December) before the U.S. makes any further changes. Yet, prompt actions and reform have not been characteristic of the Castros, who have already outlasted ten American Presidents.
The U.S. should not wait on the Cuban government to make further changes that benefit the Cuban people and are in our national interest. The U.S. should continue to readjust its policies to utilize our best asset, the American people, to engage with the Cubans and help in turn to develop a more open Cuban society. 
(This post also appeared on  The Washington Note ) 
    
</item>
<item>
   <title>
Fuel for the Travel Fire
</title>
   <link>
SEM LINK
</link>
    tag:thehavananote.com,2010://1.490 
   
    2010-08-17T15:39:50Z 
    2010-08-17T18:50:59Z 
   
   <description>
 Representative Meek and President Obama Below are annotated highlights from a very important story about Presidential action on people-to-people travel in today s New York Times by Ginger Thompson. It makes clear why anyone who wants to improve US relations...
</description>
    
       John McAuliff 
       http://thehavananote.com/johnmcauliff.html 
    
   
   
    
         
 Representative Meek and President Obama 
Below are annotated highlights from a  very important story about Presidential action on people-to-people travel in today's  New York Times  by Ginger Thompson.
It makes clear why anyone who wants to improve US relations with Cuba should be  engaging  with and supporting the White House.
The President will be in Miami tomorrow.  Will he announce the new policy there?  How would that play for Congressman Kendrick Meek, the Diaz-Balart clone whose campaign for the Senate Obama is ostensibly supporting, although the Democrats may actually prefer Charlie Crist?
1)  Timing and content are still being debated in terms of political impact
 Congressional aides cautioned that some administration officials still saw the proposals as too politically volatile to announce until after the coming midterm elections, and they said revisions could still be made.
But others said the policy, which does not need legislative approval, would be announced before Congress returned from its break in mid-September, 
2)  The minimalist specific license bureaucratic formula is being floated
  academic institutions, including research and advocacy groups and museums, would be able to seek licenses for as long as two years. 
Just as it did for Cuban Americans, the White House ought to authorize general licenses for the full range of non-tourist travel.  It should not expand the subjective bureaucratic process of application for a specific license from the Treasury Department's Office of Foreign Assets Control (OFAC).  Processing licenses needlessly diverts OFAC from its primary national security purpose and is intimidating, time consuming and costly for applicants.
Eligibility should be determined by the declared purpose of the trip and the identity of the organizer.  An objective mechanism is to permit all IRS recognized not-for-profits to sponsor trips to Cuba, simply requiring pre and post trip notification, as is already the practice for sellers of agricultural products.
 
        3)  Senator Menendez can be discredited for confusing his talking points on opposition to all travel with the far more constrained people-to-people avenue.  
 Mr. Menendez added that promoting travel would give Havana a much needed infusion of dollars that will only allow the Castro brothers to extend their reign of oppression. 
Non-tourist travel erodes the political base of Cuban American hard-liners, but will not infuse significant dollars to the Cuban government.  At peak in 2003, 80,000 Americans traveled to Cuba, a drop in the bucket of 2.4 million international visitors last year.
4)  A more accurate description of the reason for Alan Gross's arrest is at the end of the story, which finally provides a realistic basis for negotiating his release.
 High on the United States  list of issues is winning the release of an American contractor who was detained in Cuba nine months ago when the authorities said they caught him distributing satellite telephones to Jewish dissidents. The contractor, Alan P. Gross, had gone to Cuba without the proper visa as part of longstanding program by the organization Usaid, in which development workers conduct activities aimed at strengthening groups that oppose the Castro government 
5)  More is on the table than travel
 In addition, the administration is also planning to allow flights to Cuba from more cities than the three ­ Miami, New York and Los Angeles ­ currently permitted. And there are proposals, the officials said, to allow all Americans to send remittances or charitable donations to churches, schools and human rights groups in Cuba 
6)  Robert Pastor gets the killer final comment.
 We re dealing with a relationship that s so contorted, it would take another 50 years of incremental steps to pull it apart and reassemble it in a constructive way, said Robert Pastor, a professor of international relations at American University. Even then, we re having trouble taking baby steps, when what we need is a giant leap. 
John McAuliff
Fund for Reconciliation and Development
***********************
 Links and Resources 
Specific options of people to people travel outlined  here 
Politico  story  on dubious support for Kendrick Meek
"Seizing the Opportunity to Expand People to People Contacts", a  report  from the Brookings Institution by Dora Beszterczey, Damian F. Fernandez and Andy S. Gomez
 
    
</item>
<item>
   <title>
Expectations Rising
</title>
   <link>
SEM LINK
</link>
    tag:thehavananote.com,2010://1.489 
   
    2010-08-16T15:52:11Z 
    2010-08-16T19:58:57Z 
   
   <description>
 Bill Richardson endorsing Barack Obama for President New Mexico Governor Bill Richardson contributed to the reported consideration by the Obama Administration of opening people-to-people travel to Cuba with an eloquent Washington Post Op Ed on Saturday: As a first...
</description>
    
       John McAuliff 
       http://thehavananote.com/johnmcauliff.html 
    
   
   
    
         
 Bill Richardson endorsing Barack Obama for President 
New Mexico Governor Bill Richardson contributed to the reported consideration by the Obama Administration of opening people-to-people travel to Cuba with an eloquent  Washington Post Op Ed  on Saturday:
   As a first step to changing our policy toward Cuba, the president should issue an executive order to lift as much of the travel ban as possible.  The travel ban penalizes U.S. businesses, lowers our credibility in Latin America and fuels anti-U.S. propaganda.  Lifting the ban would also be a reciprocal gesture for Cuba's recent agreement , negotiated among the Catholic Church, the Spanish government and President Raul Castro,  to release political dissidents . Obama has taken significant steps to loosen restrictions on family travel, remove limits for remittance and expand cooperation in other areas such as expanding the export of humanitarian goods from the United States into Cuba.  Loosening travel restrictions is in U.S. interests and would be a bold move toward normalization of relations with Cuba.   
Richardson's essay offers real leadership, citing Cuba as second among five initiatives to reshape US relations with the Western Hemisphere, including a comprehensive immigration law, a new Alliance for Progress with emphasis on renewable energy, trade agreements, and an accord on crime and violence.
Also weighing in  with the Administration last week in support of educational travel were fourteen national organizations, including five prominent academic groups: American Association of State Colleges and Universities, American Institute For Foreign Study, CIEE – Council on International Educational Exchange, NAFSA: Association of International Educators, and the Social Science Research Council
 
        Their  letter to the President  concluded  You have indicated that further steps would be possible in response to positive actions by Cuba, specifically including the release of political prisoners. Now that such action is being taken, it is essential that you respond, at a minimum, by removing the remaining restrictions that were imposed by President Bush. Failure to do so would not only continue to deny American citizens the ability to engage with Cuba in ways that were permissible before 2003, but would also, we fear, jeopardize the momentum toward the eventual objective that you and we share of normalizing relations with the island.
 We also encourage you to consider further actions, beyond those specified above, to facilitate travel to Cuba—specifically, to permit travel by eligible persons via general license. This will greatly ease eligible travel and will permit enforcement efforts to be focused where they are needed rather than on the administration of routine licenses.   
Close to  six hundred persons so far  have conveyed similar individual sentiments to the White House:
 
Just as you opened the way more than a year ago for Cuban American family visits free of bureaucratic impediments, you should today restore to all Americans the right to unrestricted travel for non-tourist purposes of education, culture, religion, humanitarianism, sports, dialogue, mutual understanding and support for the Cuban people. 
If the Cuban government fulfills its pledge to release its remaining one hundred non-violent political opponents, we urge that you endorse legislation easing agricultural sales and enabling complete freedom of travel (HR 4645,  S 3112). 
A bold move by the President is the best if not only means of overcoming old guard Miami funded resistance in Congress to travel legislation.  On a practical level, action now is essential for organizations to have time to set up programs for the 2010-2011 peak season.  
If travel legislation does not make it through the House and Senate this year, dramatically expanded people to people exchanges will bring much needed infusion of energy and resources for the next round of struggle.
Governor Richardson's Op Ed confirms that the President's decision on liberalization of travel is the highest priority on Cuba until Congress returns to Washington.
John McAuliff
Fund for Reconciliation and Development 
*****************
 Links and Resources 
Preparation for the opening  announced  by Cross Cultural Solutions, a leading organizer of travel to Cuba before 2004.
August issue of the e-newsletter from the Fund for Reconciliation and Development  here . 
    
</item>
<item>
   <title>
When You ve Got Family in Cuba
</title>
   <link>
SEM LINK
</link>
    tag:thehavananote.com,2010://1.488 
   
    2010-08-16T14:00:40Z 
    2010-08-16T15:29:13Z 
   
   <description>
 My home in Cuba Remember this gem from then-Deputy Assistant Secretary of State Dan Fisk in 2004?  An individual can decide when they want to travel once every three years and the decision is up to them . ....
</description>
    
       Anya Landau French 
       http://thehavananote.com/anyalandaufrench.html 
    
   
   
    
         
 My home in Cuba 
Remember this  gem  from then-Deputy Assistant Secretary of State Dan Fisk in 2004?
 "An individual can decide when they want to travel once every three years and the decision is up to them . . . So if they have a dying relative, they have to figure out when they want to travel.  
Naturally, we all applauded a year ago when President Obama finally implemented new rules that meant that U.S. policy would help reunite, instead of further divide, thousands of Cuban families, whether for beach vacations or deathbed visits. 
But there was still, of course, a catch.  If you have loved ones on the island but you aren't related by blood or by marriage, you re out of luck.  That's the position I find myself in today.  For years, I've traveled to Cuba to conduct research and to help translate the Cuban reality, warts and all, back to the U.S., where so few of us have the opportunity to get to know the largest island in the Caribbean, or the wonderful people who live there.  And in that time, I've made friends so close they have essentially become family to me and I to them.  And so it was with deep sadness that I learned this weekend that one of them has passed away.
I find myself not only sad, but angry.  Angry that a man who was like a father to me never got the chance to actually meet my father, or my husband (whom he was so happy to learn of when we found each other), or my adorable nephews back in the U.S., whose photos we all pored over together, year after year, when my work would bring me back again to the island.  I'm angry, too, that my government allows me travel to to the island for work I plan months in advance, but when it most counts, I'm powerless to be with my loved ones  right now  during this difficult time.  
Never more than now have I personally felt the damage our travel ban can do.  In spite of the foibles of our two governments, in spite of all of the water under the bridge between our two nations, there must be so many people just like me, who first traveled to Cuba as part of an exchange and ended up making lasting bonds with the warm and open people we encountered there.  
I often wonder if Dan Fisk regretted those infamously callous words of his, in justifying the separation of Cuban families across the straits of Florida.  That policy is gone, but there's much more the Obama Administration and Congress could do to bring our two peoples closer.  To say that the time has come to end the inhumanity would be an understatement.  That time came years ago.  One can only hope that U.S. policymakers are finally as ashamed of our idiotic, hurtful policy as I feel today. 
      
    
</item>
<item>
   <title>
Fidel Castro Turns 84: Is He or Isn t He Back?
</title>
   <link>
SEM LINK
</link>
    tag:thehavananote.com,2010://1.487 
   
    2010-08-13T14:05:15Z 
    2010-08-13T14:36:46Z 
   
   <description>
 Photo credit: AFP As Fidel Castro turns 84 today, Havana-based reporter Marc Frank offers a window into how the Cuban people feel about Fidel Castro s return to the limelight this past month.  The Cuban public, by and large, has...
</description>
    
       Anya Landau French 
       http://thehavananote.com/anyalandaufrench.html 
    
   
   
    
         
Photo credit:  AFP 
As Fidel Castro turns 84 today, Havana-based reporter Marc Frank  offers  a window into how the Cuban people feel about Fidel Castro's return to the limelight this past month.
 "The Cuban public, by and large, has welcomed their Commandante back after four years of seclusion with the warmth and sympathy one might bestow on an ailing, but wise grandfather home after a prolonged hospital stay, but in no position any longer to play head of the household." 
While some analysts, such as Domingo Amuchastegui, a former Cuban intelligence official who defects in the early 1990's, believe Fidel is reasserting himself and has never given up full control of Cuba, German scholar Bert Hoffman disagrees:
 "Fidel's staged performances do not signal his return to power. Instead, his remarks on international issues rather underscore his backing for Raúl's policies. From leader, Fidel has transformed into legitimator." 
Last week, Cuban blogger Yoani Sanchez  opined  that Fidel's reemergence proves he's never coming back.
 "We had already started to remember him as something from the past, which was a noble way to forget him. Many were disposed to forgive his mistakes and failures. They had put him on some gray pedestal of the history of the 20th century, capturing his face at its best moment, along with the illustrious dead. But his sudden reappearance upended those efforts. He has come forward again to shamelessly display his infirmities and announce the end of the world, as if to convince us that life after him would be lacking in purpose." 
Whatever Fidel Castro might be up to these days, Marc Frank reminds us how the Cuban people take it in stride.
 As one joke making the rounds has it, Castro is lying on his death bed with his brother Raul at his side and Cubans at the window chanting, " Fidel, Fidel."
"What are those people doing outside?" Fidel asks.
"Saying farewell," Raul responds.
"Oh, where are they all going?" asks Fidel.   
      
    
</item>
<item>
   <title>
Miami Mules Run Around the Embargo
</title>
   <link>
SEM LINK
</link>
    tag:thehavananote.com,2010://1.486 
   
    2010-08-12T15:57:31Z 
    2010-08-12T16:56:22Z 
   
   <description>
 Reuters  Esteban Israel has an interesting article on the system of mules that run consumer goods between Miami and Cuba. The article explains that Cubans can order items at marked up prices and then Cuban-Americans take the goods down...
</description>
    
       Nicholas Maliska 
       nmaliska 
    
   
   
    
         
Reuters' Esteban Israel has an interesting  article  on the system of mules that run consumer goods between Miami and Cuba.  The article explains that Cubans can order items at marked up prices and then Cuban-Americans take the goods down when they see family or hire others to transport the goods for a commission or free ticket.  About 60 percent of the remittances sent to Cuba also travel through such informal channels.  
It appears that despite the U.S. and Cuban governments  best efforts to regulate the flow of goods and money between the two countries, their systems are not working.  
In response to President George W. Bush's tightening of sanctions, the Cuban government stopped accepting the dollar as legal tender at Cuban stores and replaced it with the Cuban convertible peso (CUC) in 2004.  This forces Cubans to lose twenty percent of the value they originally receive through remittances when they have to convert dollars to CUC.  On top of this, the Cuban government s stores charge outlandish prices for consumer goods, as high as four times the normal price of things like a flat screen TV.  
Meanwhile, the U.S. restricts trade to Cuba, but allows Cuban-Americans to take down gifts, which this article shows are often sold for the relative bargain of three times the normal price, bringing in a tidy profit for the Cuban-American and Cuban entrepreneurs facilitating the transactions.  It seems the only losers in the current situation are the Cuban consumers.
 
      
    
</item>
<item>
   <title>
Debate in the Washington Post: What Constitutes Engagement?
</title>
   <link>
SEM LINK
</link>
    tag:thehavananote.com,2010://1.485 
   
    2010-08-11T18:24:41Z 
    2010-08-11T20:37:38Z 
   
   <description>
 Photo Credit: AP Cardinal Jaime Ortega has been busy in both Havana and Washington as of late, negotiating the promised release of 52 political prisoners with Raul Castro and meeting with key U.S. policy makers, including President Obama s National...
</description>
    
       Nicholas Maliska 
       nmaliska 
    
   
   
    
         
Photo Credit: AP
Cardinal Jaime Ortega has been busy in both Havana and Washington as of late, negotiating the promised release of 52 political prisoners with Raul Castro and meeting with key U.S. policy makers, including President Obama s National Security Advisor, James Jones.  While we do not yet know the details of the Cardinal s conversations with General Jones and several other U.S. officials, we did get some insight into the Cardinal s general outlook on U.S.-Cuban relations from a surprising source, Jackson Diehl of the Washington Post.  Diehl  writes :
 Ortega has nevertheless come away convinced that "this is something new," as he put it to me in an interview. Castro's prisoner releases, he contends, "open possibilities." … 
He suggests that a big part of Raúl Castro's agenda is improving relations with the United States so that Cuba's economy can be revived by U.S. trade and investment. "He has a desire for an opening with the U.S. government," Ortega said. "He repeated to me on several occasions that he is ready to talk to the United States government directly, about every issue." …  
"Everything should be step by step," Ortega said. "It's not realistic to begin at the end. This is a process. The most important thing is to take steps in the process." 
These are some truly remarkable statements coming from the Cardinal that embody the shift in Cuba s leadership as of late.  It is certainly hard to imagine Fidel Castro expressing his desire for U.S. investment in Cuba, as Fidel s political power was strengthened by his unwavering opposition to and confrontation with the empire.  Raul appears to be operating with a different calculus in mind.  His end goal is the revitalization of the Cuban economy, and he is willing to engage with the United States as the means to this end.  The fact that the Cuban Cardinal could travel between Havana and Washington, speaking with Gen. Jones privately and Diehl openly on the subject - sharing the thoughts of the current Cuban President with the American President's chief advisor on national security - is further proof that the times are changing.  
 
        To his credit, Diehl seems to have listened to what the Cardinal had to say (and published it) although Diehl comes to a very different conclusion than the Cardinal on what Raul s role is in Cuba and what the U.S. should do:
I don't doubt the cardinal's sincerity. But I also find it hard to believe that Raúl Castro is Cuba's Mikhail Gorbachev. If anything, he resembles Yuri Andropov, one of Gorbachev's aged and ailing predecessors, who knew the Soviet system was unsustainable but lacked the will or the political clout to change it. Ortega may be right that his dialogue with Raúl Castro is something new in Cuba. But the time for real change -- and for deeper engagement by the United States -- has not yet arrived.
Today, the Post published a  letter to the editor  from Wayne Smith, the former chief of the U.S. Interests Section in Havana, who wonders what Diehl's definition of deeper engagement must look like:
 
It is not time perhaps to begin thinking of an alliance. But Mr. Castro has said he will release most, if not all, political prisoners. President Obama had promised significant changes in U.S. policy in response to such a gesture. Where is it? . . .
What has the United States done to stimulate further changes? So far, nothing. 
Waiting until Cuba has a full democracy will not work. We need to respond now to the steps the Cubans have taken with steps of our own -- such as lifting travel controls and perhaps arranging an exchange of prisoners. There are various options, but we need to move. 
As Wayne Smith and Cardinal Ortega both surmise, democratic and social reforms will not take hold overnight in Cuba.  Raul Castro is moving Cuba slowly in a new direction, and according to Cardinal Ortega, Castro wants more engagement with the U.S.  Hopefully General Jones can see after fifty years of failure, that if the U.S. wants to influence Cuba s future, we too need to get moving. 
 
    
</item>
</apoena>
