<apoena>
<cabecalhorss> <cdrss>420</cdrss><endrss>www.pflp.ps/english/?q=rss.xml</endrss><cdtipdoc>1</cdtipdoc><dsctip>RSS</dsctip><cdfont>358</cdfont><dscfont> FPLP </dscfont><cdtipfont>7</cdtipfont><nmtipfont> PARTIDARIA </nmtipfont> </cabecalhorss>
<item>
 <title>
Palestinian Authority intelligence forces shut down conference against negotiations in Ramallah
</title>
 <link>
http://www.pflp.ps/english/?q=palestinian-authority-intelligence-forces-shut-dow
</link>
 <description>
Palestinian Authority intelligence and police forces attacked, interrupted and shut down a Palestinian national conference against participation in direct negotiations with Israel in Ramallah on August 25, 2010. Organized by Palestinian political parties, independent figures and human rights organizations, the conference was convened in order to denounce the negotiations, to be held under the auspices of the U.S. government, as dangerous to the Palestinian national cause. 
   read more    
</description>
  2000s 
  national unity 
  news 
  Statements 
  Thu, 26 Aug 2010 06:07:43 +0000 
  return 
  2393 at http://www.pflp.ps/english 
</item>
<item>
 <title>
PFLP leader arrested in Nablus by Palestinian Authority forces
</title>
 <link>
http://www.pflp.ps/english/?q=pflp-leader-arrested-nablus-palestinian-authority-
</link>
 <description>
Comrade Ahmad Al-Mesh ati, a leader of the Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine in Nablus, was kidnapped in Nablus by Palestinian Authority security and intelligence forces on Tuesday, August 24, 2010. Comrade al-Mesh ati has been  wanted  by the Israeli occupation forces for a number of years. Comrade Zaher al-Shishtari, representative of the PFLP in Nablus, said that the Front holds the Authority fully responsible for his safety and security and demanded his immediate release. 
   read more    
</description>
  2000s 
  news 
  prisoners 
  Statements 
  Thu, 26 Aug 2010 06:07:41 +0000 
  return 
  2392 at http://www.pflp.ps/english 
</item>
<item>
 <title>
PFLP rejects and calls for action against liquidationist return to direct negotiations 
</title>
 <link>
http://www.pflp.ps/english/?q=pflp-rejects-and-calls-action-against-liquidationi
</link>
 <description>
Comrade Maher al-Taher, member of the Political Bureau of the Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine and leader of its branch outside Palestine, said on August 20, 2010 that the goal of direct negotiations between Israel and the Palestinian Authority is to liquidate the Palestinian cause, not to reach a political solution, noting that it is clear from the events and actions of Israel that it is impossible to reach a political solution with an entity that demands total control of all aspects of Palestinian existence.  
   read more    
</description>
  2000s 
  news 
  Statements 
  Sat, 21 Aug 2010 22:45:54 +0000 
  return 
  2391 at http://www.pflp.ps/english 
</item>
<item>
 <title>
PPYU in Burin remembers Abu Obeida Omran with Iftar banquet
</title>
 <link>
http://www.pflp.ps/english/?q=ppyu-burin-remembers-abu-obeida-omran-iftar-banque
</link>
 <description>
The Palestinian Progressive Youth Union in Burin, south of Nablus in occupied Palestine, held a mass iftar banquet on August 20, 2010 attended by large crowds from the village of Burin and the surrounding area, in honor of the martyr Abu Obeida Omran, the Palestinian community leader in the United States who was killed in a criminal robbery and murder at his store in Houston, Texas on August 13, 2010. 
   read more    
</description>
  2000s 
  news 
  Youth 
  Sat, 21 Aug 2010 22:44:13 +0000 
  return 
  2390 at http://www.pflp.ps/english 
</item>
<item>
 <title>
PFLP joins with Venezuelan Embassy to aid refugee families in Syria
</title>
 <link>
http://www.pflp.ps/english/?q=pflp-joins-venezuelan-embassy-aid-refugee-families
</link>
 <description>
The Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine joined with the Embassy of the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela in the refugee camp of Khan Sheikh in Syria to distribute aid to poor families and the families of martyrs on August 17, 2010. Marking the celebration of Ramadan, the PFLP and the Venezuelan representatives distributed food baskets and other aid to children and poor families in the camp, as well as other Palestinian refugee camps in the suburbs of Damascus. 
   read more    
</description>
  2000s 
  Arab 
  International 
  news 
  Solidarity 
  Sat, 21 Aug 2010 22:42:43 +0000 
  return 
  2388 at http://www.pflp.ps/english 
</item>
<item>
 <title>
Abnaa el-Balad General Secretary interrogated for participating in a demonstration
</title>
 <link>
http://www.pflp.ps/english/?q=abnaa-el-balad-general-secretary-interrogated-part
</link>
 <description>
Abna a el-Balad, the Palestinian movement inside Occupied Palestine 1948, announced on August 20 that Comrade Mohammed Kanaaneh, Abu Assad, the General Secretary of the movement, had been called for interrogation by Zionist security services on August 19, 2010.  
   read more    
</description>
  2000s 
  news 
  Palestine 48 
  prisoners 
  Sat, 21 Aug 2010 22:41:48 +0000 
  return 
  2389 at http://www.pflp.ps/english 
</item>
<item>
 <title>
Comrade Leila Khaled stresses importance of internal democracy to confront occupation
</title>
 <link>
http://www.pflp.ps/english/?q=comrade-leila-khaled-stresses-importance-internal-
</link>
 <description>
Comrade Leila Khaled, member of the Political Bureau of the Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine, said on August 17, 2010, that national unity and popular democracy are critical for the Palestinian people to confront the occupation and its criminal assaults and siege upon our people.  
   read more    
</description>
  2000s 
  Leila Khaled 
  news 
  Statements 
  Sat, 21 Aug 2010 22:41:41 +0000 
  return 
  2387 at http://www.pflp.ps/english 
</item>
<item>
 <title>
Palestinian factions reject US/Zionist pressure for direct negotiations
</title>
 <link>
http://www.pflp.ps/english/?q=palestinian-factions-reject-uszionist-pressure-dir
</link>
 <description>
  
The Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine joined with Hamas, Islamic Jihad, the DFLP and 7 other Palestinian factions to issue a joint statement in Damascus in opposition to the resumption of negotiations, direct or indirect, with Israel on August 15, 2010. The joint statement, read at a press conference by Comrade Dr.     read more    
</description>
  2000s 
  national unity 
  news 
  Statements 
  Mon, 16 Aug 2010 06:13:33 +0000 
  return 
  2386 at http://www.pflp.ps/english 
</item>
<item>
 <title>
PFLP mourns the loss of community leader Comrade Abu Obeida Omran
</title>
 <link>
http://www.pflp.ps/english/?q=pflp-mourns-loss-community-leader-comrade-abu-obei
</link>
 <description>
  
The Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine in occupied Palestine expressed its mourning for Comrade Abu Obeida Omran, a son of Burin and a leader of the Palestinian community in the United States, in a statement on August 14, 2010. Comrade Abu Obeida was murdered in an attempted robbery at his business in Houston, Texas on August 13, 2010.  
     read more    
</description>
  2000s 
  news 
  Shatat 
  Statements 
  Mon, 16 Aug 2010 06:07:31 +0000 
  return 
  2385 at http://www.pflp.ps/english 
</item>
<item>
 <title>
Comrade Badran Jaber s farm in Al-Khalil attacked by occupation bulldozers
</title>
 <link>
http://www.pflp.ps/english/?q=comrade-badran-jabers-farm-al-khalil-attacked-occu
</link>
 <description>
Occupation forces destroyed over 30 dunums of Palestinian farmland in the village of Al-Baqa a outside al-Khalil today, August 2, 2010, said Comrade Badran Jaber, member of the Central Committee of the Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine, whose farmland was targeted for the occupation forces  attack.  
 
   read more    
</description>
  2000s 
  Agriculture 
  news 
  Tue, 03 Aug 2010 05:07:31 +0000 
  return 
  2384 at http://www.pflp.ps/english 
</item>
</apoena>
